You were talking about that missed call
at a treatment center. It isn't a lost
sale. It's a patient safety event.
If you and I were in selling widgets
somewhere, right? You and I would
[music] be talking about the leads that
come in. But it's harder to put that tag
on a person, especially a person that's
stuck in addiction. How do you call them
a lead? So, let's call them what they
really are. People that had a moment of
clarity that make a call that could save
their life and nobody answers that. If
nobody answers the phone, [music] if
it's a long hold time, a drop call, any
of those things, that could save a life.
90% of the people that call treatment
[music] center at 3:00 a.m. aren't
usually sober at the time. So, there's a
whole lot of things that they say,
slurring words, getting a little upset.
So, our AI age trained to know that
cool technology is not the solution.
It's the tailored ones that actually
help people.
Technology is not 100%. But then again,
people aren't either. You bring a
personal perspective [music] to this
work. How does that lens change the way
that you build?
I was the person that sat in that CRM
and waited for a call. We take the
clients that are inactive and then the
AI text engages them with the idea of
coming back to admissions. These are
people that the treatment center can't
call.
Oh my gosh. Welcome back to the signal
room. I'm Chris Hutchins. My guest
today works at one of the most sensitive
doorways in all of healthcare. the
moment someone picks up the phone and
asks for help with addiction. David
Sichel is the founder of Blue Shirt
Media and he builds AI that answers and
follows up for drug and alcohol
treatment centers. What pulled me in is
how he how careful he is about it. This
is a conversation about doing automation
responsibly when mistakes are a human
life. Dave, welcome to the Signal Room.
Thanks, Chris. It's a pleasure being
here and I really enjoyed our
conversation on Friday also. I did as
well and I'm really excited for for you
to be able to share your story with with
our listeners today. Maybe just kind of
start with the short version of who you
are and what Blue Shirt Media does.
Yeah. So, I'm Dave Sichel. As we
discussed on Friday, I'm a person in
long-term recovery. I have experience
before this uh situation happened before
I formed this company. I have experience
with building a another company that was
a transport company that would take
people to treatment. And when I was in
there, like most things in life that
happened to you, I saw the emissions
department and how overworked them,
right?
But for CO did and there was no
anything, no certainty on how the
protocol would be to take people to
treat, right? So I shut that business
and then what happened is I realized
that later on once AI came out that
there was a gap
in the treatment uh that phone calls
would go with miss without being
answered and PE and emissions people
couldn't get the calls. So AI a pain
point and here we are. Yeah, the there
was so much revealed during the during
those early days of COVID. U you know I
I know people been disrupted you know
hearing what you're telling me about
your having to shut down your business.
I'm sure that was not a there was plenty
of stress in that I am certain. So in
our conversation Friday you said
something that really kind of stuck with
me and I really want to dig into this a
little bit. You were talking about that
missed call at a treatment center like
you just mentioned. It isn't a lost
sale. It's a patient safety event.
Unpack for me what's actually on the
other end of that mis call.
Yeah, Chris. So, for me, when I'm in
this business, it's hard because not
hard, it's it's rewarding. But when I
when if you and I were in, let's say,
selling widgets somewhere, right? You
and I would be talking about the leads
that come in. That's what we you and I
would be discussing. But it's harder to
put that tag on a person, especially a
person in addiction that's stuck in
addiction. How do you call them elite?
So, let's call them what they really
are. People that had a moment of clarity
that make a call that could save their
life and nobody answered that.
Oh my gosh, that's profound.
Yeah. Joe, as you you know, we discussed
on on our previous call, you know, when
we talked last week, we discussed that
there was only a certain amount of time
that people and anybody that has that
has experience with a loved one, a
friend, a family member, whatever
addiction, you know, firsthand that
person isn't ready until they're ready.
Yes. So when their courage up or the
will to I don't or the desperation
there's a million words I could use
there but we'll make it easy when they
finally that call if nobody answers the
phone if it's a long hold time a drop
call any of those things then if
nobody's on the other end of that that
that's the difference between that could
save a life
100% that's so profound I'm glad you
glad you put it that way too because we
try to do our best but sometimes that's
not enough. And I and I just I love that
you're you're putting this a clear focus
back on the individual who's just had
that moment of clarity. And we have to
pay attention and we have to do better
if we're going to use AI for good. These
are the types of things we have to keep
in mind. So let's talk about, you know,
what kind of brought you to this. So
take me back to how you ended up
building this uh why treatment center
specifically and why the front door.
Yeah. So what happened is it's a good
question. What happened was I thought of
the idea and then what happened was I
joined a platform called go high level
which a lot of people have heard of
which is a good platform the issue for
me that I had was that it does a lot of
good things right a lot of things but
it's not perfect in anything and I knew
that for the importance of this call and
the value of this call I had to get
agents a uh answering that would be a
100%. Right.
Yes.
That would be a model that I could roll
out and people could listen and say,
"Oh, Chris, that's so empathetic, you
know, uh, that person really don't
really they identify like an agent. They
identify as an agent, but then you will
never know once you start talking."
That's the one I went through. So, I did
some work with a white label and I but I
still wasn't controlling it. So I went
inhouse and started my own tech working
on my own tech stack. So now it's me, a
developer, a VA, and we're building our
own custom models.
You bring a personal perspective to this
work. Share as much or as little as you
you'd like. How does that lens change
the way that you build? Well, as far as
what I built, I have this this pressure
or whip on my back, let's say, that I
just never feel as good as anybody says
it is, as great as an idea, as the
product is, and it works really well,
that it's good enough, that it's always
going to, you know, again, let's not
fool ourselves. As great as it is, and
as great as everything is, it's still
technology. And you you know you know
technology technology is not 100%. But
then again people aren't either. That's
right.
You know what I mean? But I believe it's
such a gratification to know that even
though I'm never happy with it because
it's never good enough for me that at
the end of the day I'm building
something that saves lives. And you know
as far as the personal perspective I was
that person. you know, we're going to
talk about in a few minutes about what
we do lead reactivation, but you know,
as far as the personal aspect, I was the
person that sat in that CRM and waited
for a call that came. So, as on a
personal perspective, my personal goals
align with my business goals and that is
in my life to to help as many people as
I can. I I love that Dave. I mean that
was crystal clear the the first moment
we spoke that you've got a passion for
what you're doing. I think that really
matters a lot because people are in
various stages of life. All of us are
dealing with some really crazy times
that we're living in and all of us are
experiencing very common things and more
often than not they don't get any
airtime and I think it's just really
important for people to hear how things
really are so they understand they're
not alone and it actually is okay to
reach out for help and how you're
conducting yourself and driving your
business where you spend your time what
matters. It's a beautiful thing and I
really do appreciate how you do that.
Let's talk about mistakes just a little
bit. Most AI answering pitches are about
efficiency in your world. The caller
might be the worst moment at the worst
moment of their life. What does that
change about how the system has to
behave in the first 10 seconds for
example?
And in what what it's allowed to say? I
mean I mean there's a
Well, first thing we Yeah. And I I think
I got your question, but first thing we
say is on the call is we tell them that
my name is Jody or John or whatever it
is, guy, girl, and this call is being
recorded for quality purposes, right? We
record that break that down right there.
We record that call in case there's any
questions for the treatment center
because we try to pass the data
anonymously to the center because you
know and again we'll get into that into
HIPPA and different privacy things. So
we always stay compliant. So for the
first 10 seconds of the call, it's just
really and also we let them know which I
feel is a really good add-on is that we
send a text message at the end of with
their permission. If they say no, we
don't opt them in to the text message
with the call. So we say, you know, that
you know also we'll get a summary text
message and that text message I just
want to say works twofold. First of all,
the information goes right into the
client CR. This is all in real time,
right? And then the other thing that
that text message that we're talking
about, we could also set if it's an
overnight center, right? If that we're
answering overnight, we could do one of
a few things.
a live transfer, which a lot of people
prefer. It's hard to harder to do at
night than it is at 3:00, but at 3 p.m.
But the other thing we could do is with
that text message, we could send the
client a reminder or we could do an AI
call reminder to the client 7 a.m., 8
a.m., whenever they open. Hey, Joe, it's
Dave. You know, you were speaking to us.
We just want to let you know, here's the
number to call. And the uh the center
will also have the information. So the
first 10 minutes, first 10 seconds, I'm
sorry. The first 10 seconds, we're
really getting information out of the
way and then we wait to see what's going
on. You know, basic questions that we
have. thought and I'll just say this too
as the call progresses our AI agents are
overnight answering calls and daily
answering calls are known know that a
lot of people that call treatment center
at 3:00 a.m. I would say 90% of the
people that call treatment center at
3:00 a.m. aren't usually sober at the
time,
right?
So, there's a whole lot of things that
they say, slurring words, getting a
little upset. So, our AI agents trained
to know that to to be slower. So, I know
I jumped a little bit ahead on that
question, but yeah. So, uh yes, so that
that's what our agents do. Yeah.
Yeah. But I think it it leads naturally
to the to the question around, you know,
what are the stopping points? So, you
know, you're clear that it's not going
to give medical advice, but walk me
through where the machine stops and and
a human becomes involved.
So, what happens is a human becomes
involved a couple ways. The first way is
we I would like to say we have all these
programs and this and that, but what we
do is we sit down with the treatment
center and we say to them, look, Chris,
what qualifi?
You know, like maybe for a treatment
center it might be we accept this blue
cross. I just making but when do you
what's your level? It's really you know
we don't we don't decide. What's your
level on where the call needs to
escalate to an agent? So that just leads
me into this what we had talked about on
Friday is that our the biggest
misconception we you know we both spoke
about it was is that AI is replacing
people. Our AI is just a tool to answer
more calls and to free up emissions
people to only be able to react with the
follow, you know, to the calls they want
to react to and take, you know, so what
which really we call it the bandwidth in
the treatment center which really
reduces the band bandwidth and frees
them up a little bit more which we
really like.
Yeah. And during our conversation, I
think we we mentioned we kind of hit on
this governance theater issue. You know,
the councils that perform oversight
without actually doing it. Um, in a
setting this sensitive, what does real
governance look like versus the show
version?
When you mean real governance, uh, do
you mean like what we do on our part to
make it is that what you're going like
what we we you know, we have to sign
agree.
Go ahead. I'm sorry. Now it's really the
rather than having these lofty
conversations around governance and it's
all an academic exercise. What does it
actually look like in practice? So for
example, you have to come to some
conclusions and build some rules around
what the human escalation pathways are
and what are the things that cause that
to kick in. And these are decisions that
have to get made. They're not, you know,
oh, we'll just we'll just win you and
hope it works.
And everything we were saying earlier
about the call, how the moment of
sanity, you there's no room for error in
what you're talking about right there.
So, what I say is, and you know, I I
alluded to it a little bit before, but
what I say is that we don't we design
what they want.
Yeah. I do the we do the technical
stuff, the prompts, and this and that.
still it you we sit down and we go over
everything first in our process is I'll
build you a demo right and the demo will
you it'll just be something I c got off
the web with your information right so
that's a demo you listen to it listen to
her voice his voice I keep saying her
but male ages too listen to her listen
to the voice tell us what you think and
I always say the same thing to people
it's part of my thing I'm like look if
it's not up to what you got I I can't
make you know it's never if you don't
like the overall tone there, you know,
there's not much I can do to make you
like that, right?
You know, like redundancy, you know,
like, you know, I know on certain
models, and you've probably had
experience with these personally, too.
Yeah, I think we did talk about this
too. On certain models there's a long
pause between questions and that is
because the agent is looking in the
database for right the knowledge base
for the right information right that's
slowed the call down right so what we do
is we we just put it on so if you get a
demo for us what I was talking about
just talking about if you get a demo for
us and that's not sounding right to you
then we're not the right fit for you.
You you need to find somebody else.
There's other people that do it. Not you
couldn't. But if you like that then we
sit down and we go in for the second
phase and that is all right Chris tell
us what you want in an admissions
person. Let me see write me an FAQ. I
have noticed in these things even though
with treatment it's a little bit
different
but with these questions 90% of the
people ask the same questions all the
time. You know, you can they may say
them differently or ask them
differently, but what kind of treatment
you have? How long is the treatment? Can
I bring my can I bring my girlfriend?
Can I bring my dog? You know, can I
bring Red Bull? There's a million things
I like. There's a lot of questions like
answer that we can answer really
quickly. So, when it gets into the next
stage is when they say, "All right,
Dave, they have insurance. They're ready
to come in.
let's transfer to a live agent. And in
that same token, we do also long hold
times. Another thing, Chris, you got the
call, you know, and you're on the call
and you're waiting five minutes. You may
be in we're in that same moment, right?
Yes.
You may be disconnecting them.
So, we get on the lines, try to get
information, bring it back to emissions,
you know, this call, drop code. So,
yeah.
Right.
Let's talk about the trust issue. So
there there's been I spent a lot of time
talking with folks about trust a lot
from the you know the the relationship
standpoint just because there's been
such a really horrible decay in the
relationship trust between human beings
in the last couple decades. Uh I won't
labor that but but you you've seen some
messaging channels being abused as well.
So earning trust in this arena what
under the context of governance I think
is what what I'm thinking of. you you've
seen like spam, fake approvals, vendors
waving AI generated claims around. I
mean, what does that abuse cost the
legitimate operators like you?
Yeah, that just that that I believe I've
been really been self-employed for over
over 40 years. I know I only look 30, so
it's hard to say that.
I was I was going to say, brother, you
look really awesome. 25 30
right? He's got to be lying if he's
saying 40 years. I know that's what you
were thinking.
So, um, so the answer to your question
is is that we put on a a really good
product, but I've been dealing with that
kind of stuff no matter whether I was a
kid hustling candy
or, you know, you know, onto this AI.
But to your point, there is a higher
abuse with this AI and there's also a
problem with people contacting treatment
centers and home service business
everything about using their AI, you
know, like people get contacted 100
times a day.
Yeah.
You know, for so Yeah. So, as far as I'm
concerned, there's always bad actors and
everything. We don't we don't everything
for us has to be 100% clean. We want it
to be right. Want to be compliant and we
want to you know get our get our message
out that look you you know you never
have to miss a call.
So here's a another interesting angle
that you know I I wouldn't I would hope
would never be an issue but but it
actually is. We got back to the trust
factor. How do you tell a center odor
it's automated without it sounding like
you've put a robot between a desperate
caller and help?
Yeah, I we don't have that problem. Our
our people sound human. Our ages and I
my bad because I told you Friday I'd
send you a demo and I never did. But our
I would like your you to hear them too.
But yeah, we don't sound anything like
an automatic automated robot. And that's
been my whole purpose started. And the
good thing about AI is AI has come a
long way in the year I've been doing it.
You know, just better, you know, more
tools available and uh the treatment
center owner has to be on board or the,
you know, head of business development
or whatever their title is has to really
be on board. And here with this, like I
said, a five minute test before they go
anywhere. And I expect people, whatever
works for you, whether it be me or the
next guy, that's fine with me. But I'm
always going to put my best forward. But
I can tell you this, as far as
governance and that stuff goes,
the agents, to answer your question
specifically, the agents a year ago to
the agents today and the agents in six
months are so much better, so much
clearer. Our agents learn so much. The
agents that we have out there, you know,
come in and we take information just not
names and stuff, but information
anonymous data and we run that into the
AI to see where, you know, where can we
improve. So, we're always working on our
models. We don't sit back and say,
"Well, you know what? Today we have the
best model and or you know, so we just
keep going." It's important.
Yes. I I couldn't agree with you more
and that's one of the things that's
challenging for people to wrap their
head around is if you're using software
typically there's cycles. So, you know,
maybe there's an upgrade every quarter,
every other quarter. There's, you know,
patterns like that. But this is a
situation where the models are evolving
almost on a daily basis. It's just it
just needs a lot more eyeballs on it on
a regular basis than we've ever had to
have before. So, I mean, I definitely
appreciate the the approach you take to
it. If we could zoom out just a little
bit from the treatment centers, if you
were advising any healthcare
organization that standing up AI at a
human critical touch point, what's the
one principle you'd make non-negotiable
on a human touch point? Let me see if I
got that. So what you're saying is if I
would, you know, a hospital or a
doctor's office, anybody else outside
the treatment space, what would I make a
non-negotiable for a handoff, right, for
uh live transfer?
Exactly.
Yeah. So I I would make sure it would
first of all that the AI agent would
identify itself as an AI agent,
right?
That any disclaimers in the in the
beginning recorded, you know, because
healthcare is healthcare. any disclaimer
they all everybody's with HIPPA here so
any disclaimers that they have recording
like we said text message if the case so
in the beginning I I would just kind of
let people know that it's an AI right
before I went anywhere then I would get
into the calling you know to the prompt
and I would write I would tell people
look you would I would ask people how
far do you want to go with it we can
keep the AI engaged for 30 minutes or we
could if your idea is just answering the
phone times are busy and just getting
the call to a live person then we can go
really fast. So a a non-negotiable for
me would be no communication. I have to
know from you what you want to do
otherwise doesn't I can't do it. I won't
do it.
I love that. It's a crystal clear
answer. We don't get those often enough
these days it seems. I appreciate that.
I wanted to kind of look at another
angle of it. You know, we're we're
coming close to the end of our time and
I want to make sure we hit a couple
really important things. Where do you
think the industry is getting
responsible AI wrong right now?
I think it's hard for me to say that as
I am low low I do follow AI things, you
know, everywhere, but it's mainly from
my software providers. So, it's really
hard for me to say where they're getting
it wrong. The only experience I can give
you as is as a consumer and I'll hear a
I'll call an AI
think with the city I live in which
we'll leave anonymous because I live
here. I'm kidding. But what you know
like it's a terrible AI you know AI I
think that if you put a product out no
matter what the business home service
doctor whatever it is and it's not and
it makes the person want to hang up or
if it makes the person just confused
then either one of two things you don't
care or your callers don't mean anything
to you. So I would say an incomplete
product people not taking the time to go
over things. I really Chris only know
from my perspective and I know how hard
we go over things but it has given me
the ability to text other AIs listen to
video you know to different AIs and
within 15 seconds I could tell you
whether they spent time preparing that
or not.
Yeah that's a it's it's interesting. So
I think being in healthcare from the
majority of my career, I think that I've
seen so many solutions that come and
they're they are really narrow. They're
tackling this much of a space that has a
broader set of needs and it just seems
like we're picking and choosing these
little components but never actually
solving the whole end to end and it just
it's just really pro problematic to work
that way. So, you know, I think this
this whole idea of really making sure
that we're developing things that are
really fit for the purpose that they're
that they should be is it's just
important. Cool technology is not the
solution. It's the tailored ones that
actually help people. That's what really
matters.
Yeah. Yeah. And if I could add to that,
I would just say that the most if your
callers are important to you and like if
that's your first line of defense, which
most people are for sales,
Yeah.
is your call. come in. If you just want
to save money, you can find
um many models. You there's plenty of
people that will do it,
you know, uh really cheap, have a really
cheap model. You'll get, you know,
you'll pay less than maybe any major
vendor would charge you. The problem is
is with that is people know, you know,
it's AI. Like if your if your sign on
your business is a $5,700 sign instead
of an $11,000 sign, people might not
know that. But if you're, you know, so
why I say that is because we build a
done for you system. We don't build a
piece of software and give it to you,
you know. We do, you know. So I think
that people know the difference. And as
we go more and more and more people that
say they, you know, never go to AI go to
AI.
Then we'll see even more. You'll know
and you know too. It's not just me.
Everybody knows when you're calling a
bad AI. You just want to talk to the
agent right away. If my people if people
are calling my AI and I have used it in
other industry, if people are calling my
my AI and they're not and they're
hanging up or they're losing calls, then
it's just not the right product,
right?
I'm not doing my job.
So, last couple of things. So, for
someone who's running a center and
they're hearing this and think, "hm, I
think I might need to fix my front
door." What's the first thing they
should do?
What do you mean fix your Did you say
fix your front door?
Yeah, they're they realize I they need
to fix the front door. What you mean?
What should they do? Should should they
try to solve this with or without a
vendor? What would you recommend? Yeah,
I I would suggest that you would get
somebody that that you feel comfortable
with, that you trust, that you see
information about on the web, you know,
that you could research. But more
importantly, with all that said, I say,
not just because it's the way I do it,
but let them run a demo for you. I would
say do, you know, do that. See how it
is. You know, it's proven that it will
work in this industry, right? Uh, so you
know, just find take your time, try a
couple different people and see where
you're the most comfortable. I hope it's
me, but if it's not, you know, use the
next guy,
right? No, I appreciate that. Well, this
between last Friday and today, our
conversation, what's a question maybe I
should have asked that I didn't ask? Did
you want to speak?
Yeah. What I do want to say really
quick, it'll only take a minute is we do
something else too where we engage
inactive clients, right? So every
treatment center has and this I really I
said to earlier in the uh interview I
was saying that I was that guy. So yeah,
so we take the clients that are inactive
and what we do with them is we get the
client uh commercially approved for text
messages and we send a text message to
them and then the AI uh text engages
them with the idea of coming back to
admissions. These are people that the
treatment center can't don't have
doesn't have the time or can't call. So
that's something we do. Yeah, we're very
not a lot of people are doing that. uh
right now we're one of the few but you
know we're we're uh it's it's really
important to me can help a lot of
people.
No, I totally get that and it seems like
an obvious place where technology should
be part of the process that people think
about but I mean it's an area where I
mean I just love that you're taking
think taking the proactive step if and
not just leaving it and hoping that
they're the center is going to do those
follow-ups. I think that's a that's a
differentiator from from where I sit.
So, where can people find you and where
can they find out more about blueshirt
media?
Yeah, so you can go to my site. I think
we talked about there'll be a link
there. It's blueshirtmedia.com.
You can uh also uh you know go to my
site, come there, read the blogs, read
the information, call me my you can call
me directly on my cell phone. We'll go
over anything you want to go over. And
even if you're maybe not in the
treatment space, but you're somewhat in
healthcare and you want to find out some
options, we really do talk to, you know,
people that can use the service that
doesn't don't even know it exists. So,
blueshirtmedia.com.
Thank Thanks so much, Dave. I really
appreciate it. And for our listeners,
you'll find all the contact information
you you could ever need in the show
notes as always. And please don't
hesitate to to reach out to Dave and and
his team at Blue Shark Media. Dave, this
has been a amazing conversation. Well,
two days worth of it. The guests only
get to the excuse me, the the our
listeners only get to hear today's
version. Um, but I very much have
enjoyed our conversations and I look
forward to continuing those. And thank
you so much again for what you're doing.
You're missionoriented. You've got
passion and it's personal. To me, that's
the winning formula to really make a
difference in people's lives. So, on
behalf of my listeners, I say thank you.
Thank you, Chris. Thanks for having me.
Appreciate it. That's it for this
episode of the Signal Room. If today's
conversation sparks something in you, an
idea, a challenge, or a perspective
worth amplifying, I'd love to hear from
you. Message me on LinkedIn or visit
sigaroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming